Birgitta Böckeler is a distinguished engineer at Thoughtworks.
And I've been chatting to
for a little while and actually was really impressed by a
very a post that went viral on Martin Fowler's site that Birgitta wrote
talking about specs and talking about the comparison
at the time between Spec and Cairo, I think it was.
And okay, Tessl has moved on a little bit since then, but it's still amazing
to see how many people go to go to that site.
It is an amazing person.
I very much encourage you to to follow her.
She's she's very thoughtful with so many posts and blogs that she writes
and a really wonderful way to finish off this conference
with a very visionary session whereby we begin to
is going to look at the last 12 months where
what's been changing, where we are today and what we can look forward to.
So please give a very native dev warm welcome to Birgitta Böckeler.
Okay.
Thanks, Simon.
Thanks, Simon and Patrick for inviting me.
Yeah. So I'm a distinguished engineer at ThoughtWorks.
And what that means for me specifically is that three years ago,
I got a full time role to just be immersed in the space of AI
coding, or in general,
using AI on software teams to help my colleagues to help our clients.
I kind of stay on top of it.
So I talk a lot to our teams, our clients, and so on.
And then I write about it, for example, on my colleague Martin Fowler's website.
And so that's kind of like what all of this is based on.
And yeah, it's kind of like a tough task of wrapping up
after everybody heard about this topic for two days.
So I'm going to try and help you see the forest for the trees
or the multiple forests for all of the the trees.
So I kind of do like a recap.
I'll start with the recap slide.
Simon was briefly confused and thought
maybe by slide side I was wrong, but it's kind of like recap
a lot of what the stuff that you heard also over the last two days, but also
kind of what happened in the last 12 months,
like advancements as well as things that are
maybe not going so well or that are kind of like the or the second
order consequences and implications that we're experiencing right now.
So that when you get back to work tomorrow and your colleague who maybe
isn't as immersed in the space as you, so what should I know, right?
I hope I can help you answer that question.
And I'll start with, yeah, the reason why all of this is happening,
which is the model.
So kind of first and most obvious, there wasn't even that much talk
about models here at the conference, I think,
which is not surprising and totally okay, I think, because for me,
this is not really the most exciting part, to be honest.
I'm much more interested in everything that's now happening around it
the ecosystem, all of the integrations and so on.
And I mean, obviously,
if we talk about the last 12 months, there was the Claude Opus 4.5 moment
kind of last year that made a lot of people kind of like
come back to this that hadn't maybe tried AI coding for a while.
And
yeah, so that was maybe the biggest event and models that happened like,
I mean, almost every week there's a new model,
but I usually don't even follow it that much because like I said, it's
kind of interesting to see all this stuff around it.
So if we think about models like what are the core things,
kind of as users who use them for coding that
we need to know or learn, almost like a kind of like learning map, right?
So the first thing I always try
to get out of the way is that they are not magic, right?
They are very, very impressive and very, very useful math.
But unfortunately, even like a lot of technologists,
a lot of our peers kind of like it's very easy to fall into that trap
of thinking of them as, as more than that.
Right?
So I kind of like this visualization to remind ourselves that, you know,
even though we don't really know what's like,
why it works and what's happening, it's still like very impressive math, right?
So first of all, they're not magic.
I mentioned here as the second point there, statelessness,
because that's also something that I often noticed that people haven't quite grasp.
Right.
So the model doesn't have a session, right?
So the longer our conversation with them gets, the longer our session with them
gets every single time the our agent,
our harness basically sends the whole history of the conversation.
Right.
Maybe not quite this caching and all kinds of clever ways
that different tools try to optimize that, but they are stateless, right?
So that is a factor that happens like the longer our conversations
get with them.
So I think that's a really important core thing that
yeah, people need to understand.
The third thing we need to know about is,
of course, the size of the context window and in relationship,
but also in relationship to what that means for attention. Right.
So even though technically the context windows have gotten a lot bigger,
it comes with the trade off on like how well the models are able
to keep attention on all of the many instructions
and all of the contexts that we're trying to feed them now.
So there's something there to be understood
by everybody who uses this about what that trade off is.
And then finally there's this.
And that's maybe the biggest area.
So those first things are kind of like you can learn them in a formal training
and kind of like understand the basics. Right.
But this last one is a lot more about using the models and figuring this out.
Right.
Which model do we use for which task. Right.
So there's I mean these are just like a few illustrative
examples like we have autocomplete.
Like there's still people who use that a lot let's say.
Or let's say you want to
just change a few specific files, and you have very clear instructions
and a very clear idea of what you want to do.
You have a larger and more complex change that needs a bunch of code research
before the model actually does it, or the agent actually does that.
Or you have like
tasks like planning, debugging, designing that maybe have a lot more like
things like asking you questions and a lot more reasoning involved.
So different tasks will have different levels of reasoning
that are useful, will need different sizes of context,
and will have different levels of need for tool calling.
And I actually think that in this area here,
we don't even have to know that much about the details of all of the different
features of the models,
but it's a lot more about us reflecting on these types of tasks, right?
Which is something that we've done in the profession for for a long time.
Right.
Like all of those
like philosophical discussions about what does complexity mean, right.
Like that we have in in estimations or stuff like that.
Right.
So you have to think about how many files might this involve.
what's a blast radius?
How much uncertainty do I still have all of those things.
So I think yeah, like I said, I think it's much more important for us to
to work on this, like reflection on the types of tasks that we have
and then match them to different levels of power that the the models have.
And if you've been bathing in powerful models
for the last few months, then it's actually a nice exercise
to remember what we're already taking for granted these days when we try
to run a smaller model on our developer laptop, right,
and try to see what it can do and what it cannot do.
And so here is like an example.
This is just to show you kind of the speed right.
The speed has actually come a really long way.
So this is when 3.6 running on my Apple M3 with 48GB of Ram.
And it's actually not even that much slower than like some of the stuff
that happens in Claude Code with with Sonnet or Opus.
Right? This is this is open code by the way.
So the speed has actually come quite a bit of a way.
Tool calling is still kind of even with this like quite powerful model
that I could hardly even run on a 64 gigabyte Ram MacBook.
So it crashed after my my first attempts to use it.
So even that model was still struggling
a bit with tool calling, which is really crucial for our workflows.
Right?
But it also has gotten a lot better than it than it was like,
I don't know, six months ago or so.
And complexity of all the instructions, I mean, you know,
many of you might have seen this when you when you try smaller models or
I remember when I first used Gemini for, for coding like a year ago.
So I kept I kept getting these these as well.
So that is still happening.
But at the same time, like I was for example, recently with GEMA
for which is like a model that everybody is talking about right now
in terms of like a smaller model that is quite capable at coding
comparatively, you know, to, to other small models.
And so I use this recently.
Again, this was the type of task
where I knew exactly what needed to be done,
but I couldn't be bothered to type it out myself.
Right.
So I gave it like one small paragraph of instructions,
and I was actually really good at doing that.
I went after that back and forth a little bit,
had it refactor it a little bit because it was quite psychologically complex.
And then I had my little utility script.
So for this I could actually use it on my, on my M3.
Right.
So again, it's a lot about like knowing the tasks
and then kind of mapping that to the level of power you want to use.
So moving on from the model and the next thing that we have around
the model is what, what we've now kind of come to calling the coding
harness, right.
Or also sometimes more colloquially still like the coding agent.
Right.
So that's the thing
that's kind of helping us leverage the model for our coding tasks.
And it has things under the hood like a system prompt or all kinds of like,
like other prompts that we usually can't even see unless it's open source.
Right?
I mean, we recently got a glimpse into the Claude Code ones, but
a lot of them are a lot of the big ones that we actually use.
A lot are closed source, right.
It comes according to answer comes with a tool, integrations,
all of the standard stuff that will definitely need right?
Changing files, reading files, code search is a big one, right?
So we get like a type of code
search out of the box, which each with each harness that we pick,
it has like all kinds of orchestration like most of them have subjects
now, for example, and also decide when to spawn off certain subjects.
Or they kind of decide like how many tool calls
at once they pass on to the model and all of those types of things.
Maybe there's some caching involved in some of them.
They have a user interface, of course, right.
Like some of them have a terminal based user interface.
Some of them are like in VS code or or other more graphical user interfaces.
And they also all come with different levels of extensibility and observability.
So extensibility famously the pi coding agent is very popular right now
as one that has brought that more to our attention of having
a coding agent that we can actually like that is malleable, that we can change.
Right.
And observability is also a space where
there's a lot happening right now in terms of,
you know, having traces of what the agent is doing,
how can we use that to, for example, analyze more like how we can improve,
how we're using the agent, getting some visibility into, for example,
I've done some stuff about visualizing for myself during a session.
Which files is it reading and which files is it writing.
So I could get an idea of like last radius of stuff.
So I think there's still a lot of potential here for us to also
make these things part of the the review cycle.
They are kind of like first rumblings about the bloat, right?
We always have the cycle in software, right?
We we get like a new tool like let's say spring, right?
And it's like super lightweight.
And we're excited
because it's much more lightweight than the bloated thing that we had before.
And then it takes like a number of years.
Right. And then we kind of feel like that's also too big, right?
With Claude Code,
it hasn't even taken a year, and we feel like it's maybe a bit much.
Right.
So here's like a comparison of like when you start out with a session in pi
versus OpenAI, Codex versus Claude Code, all of the stuff that's already in there.
Right.
But yeah.
So we need to as when we come back to like what what do we need to know.
Right.
What do we need to understand as, as engineers using these tools,
we need to kind of like understand
these features and how they distinguish between the agents.
Right.
So just to give an example, I remember when Claude Code came out
and it became super popular, I saw a lot of conflation
of the interface with the reason why Claude Code was good.
Right.
So I saw that for a while that people said, oh yeah, terminal based.
That's the way to go because it's really powerful.
But actually when you have, for example, one of my favorite harnesses
next to Cloud Coders, cursor is also really, really good
under the hood with all of those things that you see in the circle below there.
So it's not necessarily because of the terminal.
Right.
So this is just like an example of why it's it's important to kind of distinguish.
You know, kind of know as the engineer
what's actually happening in the tools.
So yeah, we have to understand that footprint, understand their features
so that we can use these features effectively. Right.
And so most like one of the big things that we want to do is
we want to understand how to regulate the context,
how to tune the context that we give to the agent
with the use of the features that the coding harness provides us.
Right.
So about 12 months ago,
the main way that we did that was rule files or instruction files.
Right?
So we would have AGENTS.md or claude.md and maybe write down the typical pitfalls.
And we're still doing that.
But these days of course, there's so many different like features
in the coding harnesses that help us do that in a more sophisticated way.
Right?
So the skills of course, MCP servers also existed about a year ago as well.
There's now subjects, there's extensions, plugins, hooks, all of those things.
And it's becoming a bit overwhelming and confusing.
Right.
But it's kind of like the storming phase of this, of this technology.
And this is also how to use these features is, I would say, was probably at least
like 50% of the talks at this, at this conference as well.
Unsurprisingly.
So it's kind of context engineering for coding agents.
And that means we're expanding the harness.
We're using the features of the harness to
to help us do this for our specific code base for our use case.
Right.
Yeah.
So we're expanding that harness.
So I'm, I'm calling it Coding Harness here.
I have to say like I'm a little bit unsure.
So this is term that that has now gotten traction since February
maybe of harness engineering. Right.
Which is basically this.
Right. Expanding this coding harness.
But in other areas, you know, people also use harness engineering
to talk about like how do you make the coding harness itself better.
Right? So it's still like a little bit clunky term, I would say.
I wish we had we had a better one.
I also jumped on the bandwagon and wrote an article about harness engineering.
Yeah, it would be great.
Maybe somebody comes up with an even better word,
like the folks at Tessl here at the conference.
They've basically
they've also had this kind of like trifecta that I'm presenting here.
Right? Like of the model, the harness and then the context. Right.
So I think it's like it's reasonable
to think of harness engineering as context engineering for coding agents.
Right.
So that's just like to get the terminology out of the way a little bit.
Yeah.
So let's look at how this area of harness engineering,
context engineering for coding agents like a mental model.
Like how I think about this like beyond the features.
Right. Yes.
This is about skills. This is about MCP servers.
But conceptually like what are we actually doing now when we use these features.
So one thing, and that's the most common thing right now
is this way of putting conventions, product context, workflow
prompts like basically markdown files into our codebase somehow, right?
Or like making them accessible through skills and so on.
And in those markdown files,
there's actually lots of different things going on, right?
We have some normative stuff like coding conventions.
We have some informative stuff like, yeah, product context.
What are we actually doing here?
Maybe reference documentation.
And then we also have instructions. Right.
Like always help me build in the following
workflow or always write a failing test first or stuff like that.
So there's actually lots of different things
going on in something that looks just like a bunch of texts at first,
and then also some of them we just have directly in the workspace,
and others are maybe more dynamically loaded from other data sources.
Right.
And so these are all for me like kind of feed forward.
So we're trying to anticipate what the agent might do wrong.
And we are also trying to anticipate of course, what we wanted to do.
And we're feeding it all of this
information, these instructions, these norms, so that hopefully
in its initial generation of code is already doing perfectly right.
But as we know, that's not always happening.
So we're starting with these guides.
But then we also want to give it feedback.
Right.
So ideally so that we can trigger immediately
a self-correction loop
before we even look at the code so that we don't have to like
have all those low hanging fruit still in there.
So the most common way that people do
that right now is with code review agents, right.
But there's also all of these other tools that we have in our toolbox
from before AI, like static code analysis.
And then of course, we can also an agent usually has access to the log
so it can start the application, see what what logs come out of it.
Many people give an agent access to the browser so it can look at like
something when it has changed a web component or something like that.
And there's actually a difference between these,
sort of like a review agent is an LLM judging the work of another LLM.
Right.
So it's kind of inferential.
It's running on the GPU, but we have a bunch of tools as well
that are computational as I decided to call them here.
So kind of things that run on the CPU, right, like the static analysis
is the best example, I think, to to think about this.
Yeah.
And we have the same distinction on the feed forward on the guide side.
So we can we can also think about computational guides on that side.
And the best example for me there is code mods Ian from meta
also just mentioned those, which is for example tools like Open Rewrite
that are really good at doing version upgrades and migrations of of frameworks.
I don't know if you remember
like quite a while ago, Amazon had a really big headline about
saving 400 or 500 developer years or something for Java upgrades
that was under the hood, actually mostly code mods being made available to AI.
So that combination is really powerful, right?
So all of these things or maybe providing a different type of code search
that is more effective for your really large code base.
All of those are ways, again, to increase the probability that AI does
what you want in the first goal.
So that's then the expanded harness.
And then as a human, as we've heard in a few talks here as well as the human,
our job in part becomes kind of steering this set of guides and sensors.
So, as Mitchell Hashimoto says in his blog post, it's the idea that anytime
you find an agent makes a mistake, you take the time to engineer a solution
such that the agent never makes that mistake again.
And of course, AI can help us engineer
those little solutions, which is really useful.
So just two quick examples to to bring that home.
So here's like something in the agent's MD do not use console log.
We have a custom logger that does structured logging and so on.
It's in the following place right.
Instead I could have like a linting rule that I customized where
I customize the message and point the agent at that log file through that.
Right.
So especially when you have things that it doesn't even do
wrong, that often that happens maybe once a week.
It's much more effective to have this linting rule than to like
stuff it into your context every single time the agent runs.
Or here's another example.
Let's say you have a back end coding conventions, a skill that talks
about the back end layers that the agent should respect in terms of
like which modules are allowed to call, which other modules.
There are some tools in most language
ecosystems that help you scan the different imports between files.
And so again, you can come up together
with AI with some rules and those tools that help you already
catch the low hanging fruit of those modularity violations.
And then
you should think about how you where you put those sensors when you run them.
Right.
So kind of like strategically think
about your path to production and think about when you want to run them.
So do you want to run them in the coding session.
Right.
Which is I think whenever that's possible in terms of like how cheap is it,
how fast it is to run a sensor, I think you should run them
like even before you commit. Right.
So I have this box here about integration. Right.
So it kind of like depends what that means for you.
So probably 80% of my commits in the last 15 years have been put straight
onto the main branch, which is probably not the case for most of you.
So integration could either be like for you to say, okay,
I want to do all of those things before I even create a commit.
Or it could be as part of the poor request process where you run
some additional like inferential sensors or something like that.
Right?
Then we have lots of stuff in our continuous integration
pipeline already, right?
You probably don't want any inferential sensors in there because you
you don't want the green or red state of your pipeline
to depend on semantic interpretation of an LLM.
Right.
But we have lots of computational sensors in there.
And then also what I've heard a lot of stories now
about teams doing in ThoughtWorks and also lots of people writing about that.
Also, the the Team Rhines team, who had a
presentation yesterday at OpenAI, they call it garbage collection.
Right.
So kind of like continuous drift detection for the technical debt
that still accumulates,
where you can probably put like a lot of inferential sensors.
Right?
So in the code base where I'm, where I'm setting up all of these things,
I have like a modularity review, like a dependency freshness review,
security review that doesn't run every single time the pipeline runs.
But I trigger it maybe like once a week just to see if there's something new
that came up.
And these like continuous drift detection things.
They probably also like require
some kind of process on your team to deal with them. Right.
There's a lot of parallels to,
for example, security vulnerabilities and how you deal with them.
Right. Like they keep popping up again.
Do you want to suppress them
because you cannot fix them right now, but then you might forget about them.
So I suspect we'll have all of these challenges there
with this type of stuff as well.
Like how is the team going to going to deal with these again?
You can maybe like have eyes.
Of course I create you can have agents create pull requests for you.
But still how do you deal with those. Right.
And then finally I should also mention this.
Of course also this way of having sensors like in production that you give
AI access to, right.
Especially when it comes to your architecture,
fitness, things like scalability, latency, all of those things.
There were a few talks here at the conference as well about using
observability data, and both to help you fix incidents,
but also just to like monitor how you can make your
your runtime better.
Okay, so
as users of coding agents, we have to know a few key model capabilities.
And like I said, kind of like
have good reflection on the types of tasks that we're that we're using
and what complexity means for us in relationship to what models can do.
We should understand the key features of harnesses
and how they differ, and not just like look at them as like,
you know, these blobs and one is a terminal and one is I'd.
But the biggest area is really this, like how do we use them to our advantage.
Right. Yeah.
How to apply this tool to our domain which is software engineering.
So with all of these things
like models getting much more capable, harness is getting much more capable.
We're kind of like getting more sophisticated and figuring out
how do we use this, how do we provide our context.
So this kind of like race continues, right?
We want more agent autonomy and we want less human supervision.
And as part of that, also something that has happened over the last 12 months
is that it has become a lot easier to run agents with no supervision.
Right.
So this screenshot is from probably last year in June, July or something.
That was the first version of Codex.
And over time now also most of the the harness products, the coding
agent products have now come, come out with like platforms
where you can always decide like, do I want to run this coding session
locally on my machine, or do I want to do it in the cloud?
And so it's become a lot easier
to do this and to to try this out. Right?
Like whatever size you feel comfortable size and complexity of tasks
you want to do this for.
Like some people run it to actually like build full features and others
maybe like just dip their toes in like
clean up this feature toggle or like small cleanup tasks, right?
And also in the meantime, we've kind of taken this like to more extremes, right?
Which is more in experimental stage right now I would say,
which is this idea of like swarms or really brute force, just sending lots
and lots of agents out there
and also having the agents decide how many agents they need.
Right.
Gastown got a lot of attention in, I think it came out in January.
There were these two like big or even more experiments from like cursor,
for example, or anthropic to build C compiler in the browser.
Cloud flow.
I think it has a different name
now that was probably even earlier than Gastown last year.
Kind of people were playing around with that.
So that's
kind of like taking it to the extreme and seeing how we can push the boundaries
and actually have AI build much bigger things more autonomously.
Yeah.
So this is our fourth year into this.
So we start with autocomplete and we had a bit
more like integration into the Ides, more context.
Claude 3.5.
Sonnet was like an early model moment I think, where I certainly from
that point on just just always, almost always use clouds on it
because it's just like felt so much better at coding than the other ones.
So then we got these like at the time, most people are.
I also, in my presentations still call it a gente coding modes.
Right.
So that's when like the the like cursor and so on.
They got like these modes
where they could also run terminal commands, which had been a thing
that was already out there in open source but not as widely used.
And so that was only about one and a half years ago.
Then shortly after that,
the vibe coding term got coined by Andrej Karpathy,
which then led to, like a lot of attention of people discovering these new genetic
modes and going, oh, this is like so that was like a wave of people
picking this up again and saying, oh, this has actually improved quite a bit.
Then we got this kind of background agents that I just talked about.
Right.
Like so Codex, for example, allowing you to run things
unsupervised in the background Claude Code is,
I think, generally available probably about a year old.
It's like it started a little bit earlier than that.
The context engineering term also started gaining traction about a year ago.
Then we had that Claude Opus moment.
We got skills OpenClaw is maybe also relevant,
a relevant moment, even though it's not quite directly about coding.
And then yeah,
so like kind of beginning of this year we got this like next wave of people
paying attention again and going, oh, this has actually changed quite a bit.
Right?
I can actually see those two yellow spots in our internal
AI coding chat community in in ThoughtWorks, I can see the spikes in
activity and then kind of like holding and then there's like another spike, like,
I don't know, 250 messages a week or something.
Median.
Yeah.
And then so yeah, the gas town and all of the swarms and all of that started.
Those big experiments started happening beginning of this year.
Then the harness engineering term has now like a buzzword.
So and you know, I don't have any additional boxes here because I think
right now it's like us all like processing, right.
And actually using all of these things that are happening.
So there's been like, I think not like a big coinage of anything
or like a new buzzword other than these things,
but we're just like grappling with it and, and using this stuff.
Right?
So it's come a long way, but the costs have as well.
And I don't just mean the token costs.
So one is security, right.
So our it's both about about like secrets potentially leaking
from our environments from our machines, but also our ecosystem is under attack.
Right.
So we have to like think even more than before
about dependency management, about sandboxing and stuff like that.
On the other hand, there was also a good talk by Joseph from GitHub
here yesterday about how we can use AI to improve our security.
Right.
So there's usually both sides to it.
Stability. Right.
So in the Dora report this was one of the big like let's say
negative trend findings about stability actually getting worse
according to their data.
But also there were a lot of talks here about how we can use
AI to help us improve our stability.
Then change ability is a big thing, right?
So like code quality defined as code that remains easy
to change and remains where it remains easy to change it with low risk.
Right.
So this was a change I recently introduced into a
still relatively new code base that was all created with AI.
And I made a change that touched 41 files, but it shouldn't have.
It wasn't like that big of a deal.
And so it was like a clear smell that there was already like accumulated
tech debt that was making changes more risky and more costly.
So but then also here the question is like,
how far can we push this more and improve this more with guides,
with sensors, with static analysis and so on.
Token cost is the most obvious costing.
Of course, in the beginning of 2024, I was at a keynote presentation
where the speaker said generating 100 lines of code only costs about $0.12.
Can you imagine?
And he was comparing that to developer salaries.
I mean, regardless of lines of code is not a measure of value, right?
Let's just get that out of the way as well.
But of course now we have like some numbers or some quotes
in the Pragmatic Engineer newsletter recently where somebody for example,
there were multiple of these quotes, but somebody said
some developers are not spending $500 a day, which,
if we take that analogy of a developer salary is over $100,000 a year,
salary, which is a pretty decent salary in the even in the richest countries
in the world. Right?
Another type of cost is like cognitive load and burnout, right?
Like, who would have thought, right?
It doesn't actually make us make our lives more relaxed.
On the contrary. Right.
Like some people are working more, even though they already create more output.
And Steve had this analogy with the energy vampire from what we do in the shadows.
I don't know if any of you have seen that that show, but he basically, yeah,
he's a vampire that doesn't suck blood, but that sucks energy.
So there's lots of stories about people saying,
oh, I can only do this like three hours in a row.
And then I have to like, take a nap.
Then we have the review crisis, of course.
Right. We have higher coding throughput.
But then can we if we can code faster, can we review faster,
test faster or ship faster, review faster?
We've definitely so far the state is no we cannot review faster.
Right.
Everybody everybody's complaining about this about this pain.
But it's not just coding.
Everybody can create more with AI now right.
So I was talking to a colleague the other day who was telling me a story
about an organization on this side of,
like, if you can code faster, can you fill the backlog faster?
So here there's like another,
another kind of like thing popping up before the coding,
where the product managers were actually, like churning out
lots and lots of prototypes and lots and lots of ideas.
Right.
So now there was this weird, like
bottleneck between this pile of prototypes and the pile of code,
because they couldn't get it to sync up again,
and nobody really could figure out how to converge
on what they actually wanted to build, because they were doing this
kind of like in these two silos.
So that's
maybe like something like an open question that we're already seeing a little bit.
But are we heading in general towards like a flow crisis?
Right.
And whenever I want to understand flow better, I turn to my colleague
James Lewis, who, like, has done a lot of very interesting presentations
about flow that it's easy to find on on YouTube.
But here's one where he's talking about congestion collapse.
And so he has this this prediction
apparently has a bet open with Gene Kim for a crate of beer, that this will happen
and that this will become like a big topic of conversation,
that we're just like overloading and also overloading in these different silos,
and that everything will just become super slow at some point and just collapse.
So this comes from things theory of constraints and stuff like that.
And here he's he's quoting the book
about the principles of product development flow as well.
So and then humans are seen as the bottleneck.
Right.
That's what multiple people also quoted or said
here at the conference.
So it remains this big question of trust in the code
and how much supervision do we want to have and how much review.
And of course it depends. Right.
So the autonomy of AI coding agents is here.
It's just unevenly distributed.
Right.
Lots of you are probably already using it for some things.
But I think it will never be that we can use
AI coding agents for any type of task in any situation.
Right?
It's just always it depends on the situation and
what does it depend on. Right?
So for me, the way I think about it right now is as this risk assessment
out of probability impact and detectability.
Right,
which is very typical kind of components of risk assessment in all kinds of areas.
So first I think about the probability that AI gets something wrong
or get something right.
And that's all about me knowing the things that I talked about before my tool,
like what my context is, did I even give the agent a chance to do it right?
And it's also about me reflecting on my confidence and my requirements, right?
Like, how certain am I even that I even know what to do?
Then I think about the impact if I get something wrong.
So that's all about the use case criticality, of course.
So is this like a super critical business flow that will wake me up at 2 a.m.
on Saturday because I'm on call?
Or is this something a lot less, a lot less important
than maybe like, I'm a little bit more loose with how I review.
And the third thing is I reflect on detectability.
That AI got something wrong, will I notice?
Right?
And by the way, all of this starts with knowing what right and wrong means, right?
I should, and often that's like is it appropriate?
Right.
So you have to know your feedback loops basically.
And then based on these things I decide which workflow do I use,
how much review do I do and how long do I let it go without supervision?
For example, if I don't even know myself yet quite what I need,
then I won't let it go off for like half an hour
and then realize that it was all for nothing, right?
And yeah, so you have to kind of be this tall to right the roller coaster.
You have to be this tall to reduce supervision. Right.
So you can think about feedback loop in your team, in your organization.
And you can also increase the probabilities by improving
your context engineering your harness engineering,
and also refactoring and modernizing and all of those things.
Because AI can also deal with a well factored code base
much better than with a messy code base.
So we're tempted to move from in the loop to on the loop to out of the loop is.
I feel this every day being drawn to like, I don't want to look at this.
I don't want to look at the code anymore.
It's like,
yeah, there's all of these forces that pull us there,
but we're also starting to actually feel the costs.
It's not just speculation anymore.
It's not just like dooming kind of predictions.
We're actually feeling the cost of tokens, risks and cognitive X, right?
Cognitive load, cognitive debt. Right.
This idea of like,
we don't even understand anymore how our code base is structured.
I sometimes think of like cognitive deferral as well.
It feels like we keep deferring the review
to other people who are like deferring processing what actually happened.
And recently there was like a new cognitive
X term coined that I saw
because Adios Mani wrote about it, which is cognitive surrender, right?
So in this paper they put AI into the context of the system
one system two thinking fast and slow.
I think probably lots of you have heard about that book.
If not, then look it up. It's like really great.
And so they're talking about a mode where we're basically displacing system tool
like our actually like active
thinking with AI and they call it cognitive surrender.
And apart from this paper and the cognitive part of it, this term
like surrender, has just been stuck in my head like ever since I heard this.
And I feel like we're there's like so many things where we're in danger
of just, like, surrendering right now, not just cognitively.
And so I think we have to be careful about what we are surrendering.
Right.
And like really think about be mindful of where that's worth doing.
So I'll just give some examples. Right.
So it's like it's too much to reason about this big change.
It'll be fine, right?
I do it myself, myself.
I just do it myself quickly instead of teaching somebody. Right.
Everybody's talking about, oh, how will juniors learn?
How will we do this?
But I don't see that much like active action.
Right.
Because everybody's just in a ton of of
I see experienced people building tools for themselves to use AI better.
But like, why are we not taking more initiative to
think about how this is sustainable for people who don't have all of this
experience already, or this like, I'll just use a big model,
you know, I can't be bothered to then like try retry it again.
So let's just use the most expensive biggest model
or the surrendering to like I don't want to solve all these problems.
Models will get better,
tokens will be cheaper again, we just have to wait it out, right?
We're working more,
we're producing more, but we're still getting the same compensation.
Is that also a type of surrender or this like, oh,
I don't have time to find
better approaches, which is, by the way, not necessarily the individual's fault.
It's also like what's happening around them and incentives and pressures.
Right?
Sandboxing is too tedious.
Surely nothing will go wrong, right?
Or I can't work on this code base without AI anymore, right?
That's the original cognitive surrender cognitive debt kind of definition.
This was like Hannah yesterday in a talk, and she was kind of talking about what
she's keeping, what she's trashing and what she's trying.
And I think that's similar in terms of like,
we have to think about what
we're surrendering and what we should be, what we should be keeping.
So if you are a person of influence in your engineering organization,
are you creating an environment that leads to a surrender?
Right.
That makes me people feel like they just have to crank out the PR
and don't have time to actually figure out how to improve
the environment, how to improve the context, engineering and so on.
If you're if you maybe feel a bit like powerless or you feel like
you can't influence it and there's all these pressures around
you still like try to think
about your sphere of influence and the small things you can do.
Like, what do you really have to surrender, right.
So there's lots of options between not using AI at all and like
just total surrender and hoping the models will fix it all in the future.
And again,
like if you feel kind of like powerless and like this is like washing over you,
we can also work together and collaborate on these things, right?
So if you feel like you're not a good communicator about this,
maybe look for somebody in your team or organization
whose good at that and share your data.
Share your observations with them. Right.
So like we can collectively do a lot about this as well in terms of skills.
We need to know our toolbox past and present.
We also need to rediscover some things.
We need critical thinking, risk assessment and some form of like patience.
Right.
So we need to evaluate that.
Productivity maybe doesn't just mean like typing.
And for leadership this is still horizon two right.
This is not horizon one yet.
So maybe we don't know the ROI yet.
Maybe we just have to like give people some time to,
to create a good setup so that we can continue to safely
and quickly deliver sovereignty users in a sustainable way.
Thank you.